IL Cafe we have you covered
thank you for joining us on Isle Cafe my
name is sheetal and the topic today is
most certainly something that I'm deeply
passionate about and I have to say I
have been privileged to have these
conversations with leaders Business
Leaders across Industries and sectors
across organizations and well the voice
has been clear there is no getting
around the need for an inclusive
workplace diversity is what really we
will explore along with inclusion and
Equity how to create psychological
workspaces and those ideas are going to
come to us from someone who's been there
and done that with a wealth of
experience in Human Resources Chief
Human Resources at icic Lombard Jerry
Jones is who we have with us today thank
you so much Jerry and welcome to aisle
Cafe hello sheetal and hello everyone
happy to be here and very very excited
to discuss about this topic this is a
topic which has engaged a lot of people
organizations leaders and I'm I'm cool
excited to basically look at various
aspects of what you described in your
opening statement yeah absolutely and so
much to cover right and so little time
so let me quickly get into the subject
over here Jerry
um there is an increasing emphasis on
inclusion and equity in organizations uh
who've already been on this journey of
building diversity so why is building an
inclusive workplace and Equity becoming
so critical to the success of any
diversity strategy so sheetal you know
most companies have realized the benefit
of uh you know diversity and they've
been on this journey of building
diversity in their respective
organizations the journey that they have
embarked on is based on a very clear
understanding of the value that
differences bring to the workplace you
know people with different perspectives
different values different uh you know
points of view different experiences and
how it can in a way help the
organization to basically leverage uh
some of these differences in order to
basically see impact at the marketplace
and see success
obviously you know there are many
benefits which is very apparent when you
have a very diverse Workforce you know
the first important thing is about
avoiding group think you know people
basically having the same kind of uh you
know thinking uh the the same kind of
norming yeah belief systems so you know
people with different perspectives can
actually come in and challenge the group
Norm which is there and basically bring
in New Perspectives which actually leads
to better innovation in the organization
it basically Fosters creativity within
the organization more importantly uh it
helps build innovative solutions to
complex problems that the organization
has been dealing with that's one
important thing that organizations see
as a benefit of people who bring
diversity to the table uh better quality
of decisions uh you know decisions
become far more richer varied and
therefore the quality of execution also
basically improves as a result of people
with different perspectives coming in
there's also a better understanding of
customers you know because you have
people from different backgrounds
experiences coming in they can relate to
customers much better than what existing
people can do and therefore there's also
a possibility of you know identifying
untapped markets and uh and and it's
quite a uh you know obvious
um thing that organization which has
diverse people within within its own
fold has better chances and is better
positioned to adapt to changing market
conditions and customer preferences you
know uh than a homogeneous group is
always used to basically managing you
know the same kind of issues and
problems so these benefits of diversity
are very very uh clear to organizations
which is why our organizations have been
pursuing this journey of diversity now
in this journey companies have gradually
realized that it is not only about
increasing the members of the
underrepresented groups yeah uh because
that alone doesn't help to realize the
benefits of diversity it is equally
important to ensure that the right
environment is created for the this
diverse group of people coming in an
environment which is conducive which
supports them helps them to basically
participate and contribute their unique
perspectives as well as talents to the
workplace so the the gradual realization
is that uh you know numbers by
themselves don't make a difference it is
primarily how the diverse talent in the
organization can be engaged so that
their uniqueness and differences can be
leveraged better for everyone in the
workplace if I were to very simply you
know Define inclusion it is basically
about saying you know is everyone in the
organization being welcomed valued
respected and empowered irrespective of
who they are and more importantly do
they get an opportunity to basically get
visibility in this organization have
their say be heard get the opportunity
to contribute and in the process to
learn grow and develop so that really
for me is the Journey of inclusion which
basically helps to leverage diversity in
a far more better way yeah that was
can't take wings and flourish if it is
not built on the foundation of inclusion
yeah because if inclusion doesn't exist
uh you know the diverse groups are going
to feel a lot more alienated they are
going to feel uh you know
disenfranchised they are going to feel
that they are they don't belong to this
place and gradually the disengagement
will happen which will actually cause
them to leave the organization and
search for newer pastures better
conducive and environment exists so it
is very it's a big imperative for
organizations to focus on inclusion in a
very big way
coming to the question of equity you
know you mentioned about Equity why is
equity becoming you know equally
important when they've been as an
organization we keep increasing the
representation of you know certain
underrepresented groups it is quite
possible that there are certain
historical or disadvantages as well as
some systemic biases that are there
within the organization within the
dominant culture of the organization
which prevents and basically hinders the
opportunities which are basically being
made available for the new people who
are coming in for the diverse people who
are coming
and therefore it does not create a Level
Playing Field for everyone in the
organization so Equity is ex is
extremely important in order to address
these disadvantages and systemic biases
uh that people face in order to ensure
that you know the treatment is fair that
equal opportunities are being made
available at the workplace which will
help diverse individuals to thrive
survive in the workplace so therefore
diversity is is more than the numbers
and the representation uh you know uh
increase that we see in the workplace it
is more about making sure that a
platform is being made available to
people in order for them to contribute
and more importantly equal opportunities
are being given to them a fair play
field is being available to them so that
they can contribute to the best of their
ability right absolutely and thank you
for you know putting into perspective
diversity inclusion and Equity very
important terms uh for every single one
of us it's not just about leaders and
organizations anymore because you need
to walk the talk employees need to
understand the need for creating these
psychologically safer spaces for us to
all flourish and thrive in so though
that was I think a great context for our
listeners I will also Point them in the
direction of resources please do read up
on ideas like intersectionality that's a
very important one to understand when
anyone is talking about diversity
um inclusion and Equity gender pronouns
and why they are used a lot of people
are still wondering why so homework for
everybody watching uh please go and read
up a little bit and that's your what you
can do towards clearing your mind of
possible unconscious biases but we will
come to biases later since you've
explained to us you know inclusive
workplaces and how you're a critical
ingredient a Jerry for the success of a
diversity strategy tell us more about
how an organization can actually create
this inclusive workplace what are the
typical things that people can do
organizations can do to create this
culture I would imagine yeah so being an
inclusive workplace uh you know involves
a massive cultural transformation you
know because it involves transforming
the mindsets of people the practices the
rituals of the organization so that
inclusion is embedded in the day-to-day
working of the organization so it's it's
uh obviously uh cultural change can't
happen uh you know without the
leadership playing a very active role
the role of leadership can't be you know
more emphasized in this journey that of
inclusion that we undertake the reason
why
um leadership plays a very critical role
in this cultural transformation is
because they have an important role to
play to prioritize give importance to
inclusion you know help transition from
the existing dominant culture which is
there in the organization you know
because any new thing which has to take
root has to basically face the
challenges of the dominant culture which
is there within the organization you
know so leaders have a very important
role to make that transition to from the
dominant culture into whatever what they
want to be or they desire to be driven
within the organization more importantly
it's they also set the new standards of
what is expected from everyone in the
organization because at the end of the
day employees need to understand what
are their own expectations in terms of
how to become a far more inclusive
person how do I basically Embark the
values of inclusion of you know trust
respect you know making sure that
everyone is heard everyone gets an
opportunity to participate yeah how do I
basically imbibe some of those behaviors
so it's important to set standards for
leaders in terms of what what is
expected from people more importantly
you also need enabling policies
practices there may be like I mentioned
earlier there may be certain policies
practices which could be restricting
which will be basically this year
addressable advantage to certain groups
in the organization how do you basically
you know eliminate or remove these
problems policies practices get enabling
policies and practices which will drive
inclusion in a very big way and more
importantly how do leaders become early
adopters yeah and role model the new
requirements yeah and expectations from
the rest of the organization so that's
why if you see you know leaders have a
role to play everywhere you know in
terms of making this functional
transformation happen and therefore I
cannot but emphasize the role that uh
you know they have in this journey
and when I say leadership I'm not
talking about top management you know
I'm referring to the larger distributed
leadership at every level in this
organization uh if you remember what I
mentioned earlier inclusion is about
making every person being seen heard
should be able to contribute yeah to be
valued now it's not possible for uh you
know people in the top Management in the
middle management to ensure this across
the organization you may have great
practices you may have great policies in
place but unless the leader at the front
line unless the leader who is there in
the field is able to basically
consciously practice inclusive behaviors
drives a culture of inclusion within his
own team we won't be able to realize
this basically ambition of driving
inclusion across the organization so it
is it is basically the responsibility of
every leader at every level in the
organization you know whether it's a
line leader who is at the front line in
the branch ensuring that his team is
getting the opportunity of being seen
heard and to contribute to the best of
their ability which will make inclusion
possible
I cannot not emphasize the role that
peers play you know we spend a lot of
time at the workplace with colleagues
they also play a very very significant
role in terms of how people experience
inclusion at the workplace how they
treat you how they basically you know
help you to get involved in the
day-to-day working of at the workplace
so colleagues and peers have a very very
important role so it's very important
that they are sensitized to what
inclusion is all about they basically
understand what are systemic devices
that exists in the workplace how can
they address it how can they make people
feel welcome the movement they enter
this organization how can they work
together the important feature about
diversity is that it has people with
differing views people with differing
value systems and this this can
potentially create a lot of conflict at
the workplace and while the leader has a
role to play to make sure that there is
he builds cohesion and basically gets
everyone to collaborate and and
basically drive them to achieve the
final objective of organizational
success peers play a very very important
role to enable this to happen because
you know how they basically behave and
treat the employee when he comes into
the workplace the diverse employee comes
into the workplace how they interact how
they behave with him it is a very
important role so the organization also
has a very important role to play in
order to Preparing the peer group The
colleagues in the organization to
basically be far more open far more
inviting to inclusion and to make sure
that the diverse Talent is able to
thrive and flourish so in my own view
leadership plays a very important role
and equally important is building the
capability of the peer group and
colleagues so that they are far more
open about the new diversity which is
coming in more accepting of the people
and therefore basically help them to
thrive and survive in the organization
fantastic you know and I'm glad that you
underlined the role that leaders play in
this whole strategy but also how the
peers are just as important in creating
this atmosphere that is welcoming and
nourishing and is transparent giving
people the opportunity to freely speak
their mind but I have to ask you this
other question right there is a tendency
that we've observed in people to make
assumptions about groups of individuals
on the basis of uh differences whether
it's religion gender you know ethnicity
and so on
the problem with this is it can really
lead to you know unfair treatment
discrimination missed opportunities
indeed for those who are the victims of
the stereotyping so what can an
organization do Jerry to recognize and
address these biases in a uh individuals
themselves and also in other people to
ensure that everyone is treated fairly
and respectfully sure so she can um you
know biases exists everywhere with every
you know groups of people it's generally
the tendency to be in favor or against a
certain group person yeah as compared to
some other individual which is typically
unfair you know so these kind of
inclinations are there across you know
the society in which we operate and also
therefore in in the corporations in
which we work the important question to
ask is that you know are people even
aware of some of these biases you know
some of them are clearly prejudices they
are aware of it and therefore
organizations obviously today are
intolerant of these kind of uh you know
prejudices that people carry at the
workplace and actively discourage them
but there is the kind of bias which
people are not even aware of which is
the unconscious bias you know because
this is these are biases which creep in
because mentally you want to basically
make quick judgments arrive at a quick
conclusion because there's a lot of
information available and therefore you
unknowingly you know rely on your own
past experiences what uh you have
learned and then take a decision based
on that so you're not even aware that
you're taking a decision which is uh
flawed yeah and therefore that comes as
a very big hindrance in terms of making
sure that you have decisions which are
appropriate which are the right
decisions the right things to do and it
impacts the organization in a very big
way a simple example I can give you is
about you know you favoring uh or are
showing basically promoting certain
kinds of people because of the
similarities that you have with them you
know it could be that they are from the
same city they may be from the same
colleges that you passed out from and
and you may do it all unknowingly you
know you uh just because you know
somewhere at the back of your mind
you're making a quick decision in terms
of how you want to judge and basically
take a decision about this person right
so I think so the first step uh that
organizations can do is make people
realize you know build capability around
this so that employees are able to
understand what unconscious bias what
are the different types of unconscious
bias that they could encounter in the
workplace yeah and how do we how do you
basically become actively conscious
about it because finally it is about
self-awareness you examine do
introspection examine what your personal
feelings are with respect to some of
these situations and the biases you
carry consciously evaluated to see that
how can you reduce the impact of these
yeah of these on the decisions that you
take yeah that's the first important
step being aware and then basically
being self-introspective and self-aware
in order to reduce the impact of these
buyers
the other important thing is about
everything is about you know how you
basically take steps to consciously
include and get to know others yeah
because your own uh circle of influence
is limited to certain groups where you
tend to have the same kind of norms the
same kind of belief systems so the key
in helping to reduce biases is to expand
your Social Circle you know it's very
important to get into uh you know
widening your Social Circle connecting
with teams peers understanding them
better because that's really the
starting point for you to be unbiased as
far as your decision making is concerned
understand the circumstances as well as
the context in which they work yeah
because that's important you know unless
you understand both these aspects you
know you tend to quickly make your
judgment about you know what is good for
them what is not good for them and
therefore take your decisions right so
that's extremely important in terms of
making the right connections reaching
out and therefore making the other
important thing is um you know how do
you create opportunities to make the
meetings far more inclusive you know
because like I said you know people
obviously may not open up it is
important for you to make sure that
people not only get the the platform to
speak but also get an actually speak out
and therefore how do you make meetings
far more inclusive if people open up
people you know very freely how do you
use inclusive language you know in
meetings because one tendency for people
is to uh you know make sure that uh you
know through their language both uh
verbal language as well as their body
language they convey certain feelings to
people where they feel uh that they are
being excluded from the decisions that
are being made or the discussions that
are being made one important thing to
remember in this entire thing is that
bias happens in the mind of one person
uh whereas inclusion exclusion happens
in the mind of some other person so all
the actions that you take in order to
remove bias yeah if you are not explicit
about it if you don't verbalize it if
you don't tell people the intent and the
objective of why you're doing it people
who are the recipients of your actions
and your decisions will still try to
draw their own conclusions in their mind
whether they are being excluded or
included which is why it is very very
important to reach out to communicate to
verbalize and say what are you trying to
do in order to reduce buyers yeah what
are you trying to do in order to make
the decisions even more fairer because
if this process is not available or not
visible to people they immediately in
their minds take the decision of sing
I'm whether I'm being included or
excluded so that's very important you
know how do you verbalize how do you
consciously and deliberately practice uh
you know inclusion in order to make
field people a part of the larger you
know organization to help them give the
sense of belonging to them so that's
extremely important and obviously you
have to promote open expression and
dialogue if you if you stifle uh you
know dialogue if you don't allow
feedback to come in that that can also
impact in a very big way uh the decision
making that people can make you know in
the organization so these are some of
the steps that organizations can
proactively do encourage it encourage
people to be aware constantly try to
basically see how to reduce the bias
biases can never be eliminated you can
only reduce the impact of the biases you
know how do you you know do that through
the larger awareness that you create
within the within the company yeah yeah
very useful pointers you know I was just
taken back Jerry when you were talking
about this too that classroom situation
we've all experienced right when we feel
that the teacher is only looking at a
few students and talking when will she
look at me and you know also uh move her
head around to see who it is it's such a
common thing that we don't even talk
about it anymore but all of us have felt
it you know wanting to sort of bob up
and down in the classroom to see if you
can get a teacher's attention so yes
it's important for us to see and also be
seen here and also be heard towards
creating this psychologically safe work
environment for people towards that
right um what are your views on uh some
of the maybe some of the trends if you
could share Jerry uh that you've seen in
creating these open communication
transparent workplaces that are
conducive to people being vocal about
who they are what they want of the
organization and from the other side
what the organization is doing as well
so it's extremely important like I said
the power of diversity comes in when
you're able to get the different ideas
from people different perspectives which
leads to Innovation and organization
success right now this cannot happen if
members don't feel comfortable speaking
up right I mean if they're afraid to
share their perspectives they're afraid
to raise concerns within the
organization ask challenging questions
it's extremely difficult for an
organization to then move forward on the
diversity agenda yeah how do people you
know share their new ideas are they
avoiding sharing new and innovative
ideas fearing the repercussions of what
will be filled by the organization if
they do that right no all these feelings
create what you mentioned as well a
psychologically unsafe Place yeah why
why does that happen because people fear
that they'll be ridiculed they'll be you
know judged they will basically be
penalized they will basically be uh you
know humiliated if people don't accept
what they are trying to share and the
belief that I can actually very safely
contribute here share my feedback uh you
know very candidly Express My Views here
share my ideas and it will be accepted
and people will you know take cognizance
of it itself builds evidence of people
of people to leverage their differences
in a very productive manner at the
workplace so it is it is psychological
safety has become such a very important
uh you know element it contributes to
inclusion happening at the workplace and
that in turn helps to leverage diversity
in a very big way at the workplace and
uh you know some of the questions that
organizations need to ask to just do a
dipstick on psychological safety at the
workplaces to basically ask the question
that if someone has made a mistake yeah
will it be held against them you know
what are the consequences of you know
making a mistake here is it safe to take
a risk you know in this team you know is
that lame game happening going to happen
is it that I will have to bear the
consequences of that that particular you
know decision which has been taken right
the other important thing is that can
team members bring up problems and ask
for help and receive it if if they can't
do that it's it's a psychologically
unsafe Place yeah so uh you know the
environment should be in such a way that
it promotes people to highlight problems
you know bring up issues and discuss
that at the uh you know at appropriate
forums and also seek for help because
you know everyone may not be know the
answers for everything if they don't do
that and they don't receive it from
their peers from colleague it is a sure
short recipe for disaster for the
organization now the other important
question or sense check to do is also
about seeing that you know do people in
this team sometimes reject others for
being different yeah or deliberately act
in a way which undermines the efforts of
other people in the team these are like
some of the small dipsticks that you can
do in order to check whether the steam
is psychologically safer and obviously
um if these kind of things don't happen
at the workplace yeah then it is very
very clear that the ideas in your
organization are are not going to be
stress test processes are not going to
get optimized Solutions won't get wetted
for whatever is being uh you know shared
by people and most importantly the
Enterprise loses an opportunity to
Leverage The contribution that all
Talent is making so that's really the
the big issue about people feeling
psychologically unsafe and it becoming a
barrier to basically inclusion as well
as you know leveraging diversity in a
very big way and and like I mentioned
you know leaders play a very important
role uh in ensuring that it is a
psychologically safe place you know
first and foremost they have to be very
very explicit and open about saying
talking about the importance of it what
behaviors that you want to see the role
models themselves and set the stage by
using these practices themselves so
that's the first step that leaders can
say uh facilitate everyone from speaking
up you know so show genuine curiosity in
people in
facilitate people to speak frankly and
tell the truth see people in a
psychologically unsafe situation will
not want to bring the bad news to the
boss yeah if they feel that they are
going to and that's such a dangerous
thing for an organization you know and
there could be several reasons for it
because they are fearful of what are the
repercussions of it however if if there
are norms established by the leader in
terms of how failure will be handled how
will this entire consequences be handled
yeah how will we use this as an
opportunity for Learning and pulling
these learnings in order to basically
then uh you know leverage it within the
organization it will encourage only
further experimentation within the team
you know it will it will encourage risk
taking to a reasonable extent within the
team otherwise you have a situation
where people don't bring the bad news
you don't know what's happening in the
organization and that's a recipe for
disaster you know once the event happens
is when you realize that this has
happened
uh the other important thing is that you
need to create platforms where people
can give feedback share ideas you know
there should be a constant flow of
information and ideas happening within
the organization in terms of how people
are feeling what are their views on this
because if ideas views information is
not reaching the doorstep of the or the
years of the leader then there is a
cause of concern because then it means
that you know information ideas views
feedback are being stifled within the
organization and there's no free flow
information which is happening and which
will impact diversity in a very big way
so readers should create the space
create the necessary platform for people
to air their views share feedback and
more importantly it is about embracing
conflict because like I said earlier you
know diversity brings different people
together and it is very inevitable that
there are bound to be certain conflicts
conflicts in terms of the value systems
that people hold in terms of the
ideation and what they want to bring it
is also important to embrace productive
conflict because that itself is going
going to bring constructive debate to
the four promote sincere dialoguing
between people you know and and people
will work to resolve this you know very
very productive way otherwise people
have just back off you know if they see
that conference no one is resolving the
conflict embracing it and basically
realizing the the benefits of a
productive conflict people are going to
back off they're not going to basically
talk about it and most importantly
finally I'd like to talk about
celebrating wins it's it's so much
important to recognize the people who do
that with Candor come up take the
courage to give the feedback talk about
it if you don't encourage that people
are not going to basically come and
discuss this with you so that's
celebrating their Candor their courage
is equally important to to encourage and
drive this kind of behavior at the
workplace obviously psychological safety
it doesn't happen overnight you know
it's it needs to be billed but
committing it to that aspiration you
know building a workplace which is
psychologically safe making sure that
the conversations are happening because
it's finally one conversation at a time
we will be able to move the needle on
psychological safety yeah and create the
necessary environment for people to you
know Thrive and flourish because they
have been given a voice to uh you know
present in an appropriate Forum so
that's really the journey that you know
organizations are traveling it's not an
easy Journey it's a major cultural
transformation like I mentioned to you
earlier right but it is well worth it
because organizations clearly see the
benefit from how psychological safety
promotes inclusion within the workplace
and therefore helps to leverage
diversity in a victory you know I like
the the phrase that you gave us over
here somehow this is going to stay with
me for a long long time Jerry which is
move the needle on creating
psychologically safe workplaces one
conversation at a time and I'm hoping
that this conversation is also moving
the needle a little bit over here and so
many actionable insights you know
because it's all very well sometimes to
talk about these things as words as
ideas but to actually breathe life into
them via action and prescribe what could
be the right way that is that is
invaluable I would imagination I would
imagine in conversations like these and
you've done that for us thank you so
much Jerry for joining us on aisle Cafe
and opening our eyes to a world when
work phrases like birds of a feather
flock together will be a thing of the
past I really hope so thank you so much
for being here
it was nice talking to you and really
enjoyed the conversation likewise
thank you you were listening to Il Cafe
we have you covered
foreign